Let us denote the set of parameters me ? so
I am going to come up with some kind of a
performance measure for a specific choice
of ?, so I will call it E(?) right so for
what is the specific choice of ? correspond
to, suppose my ? is like composed of ?1 ?2…
?K so I give you values for ?1 ?2 ?3… ? K
so what does this correspond to one, policy
when I say I am looking at a specific value
for ? it corresponds to one policy.
So when I say ? (?) that means I am evaluating
that policy something okay so what is the
most natural evaluation measure you can think
of our policy expected pay off, right expected
the expected payoff is the evaluation for
that policy so yes I am going to do I am going
to do that there okay, so what is the expected
payoff you know what the expected payoff is,
this is the expected payoff I will get for
taking action A.
This is a probability that I will take action
A when I am selecting actions according to
? right and so this is a standard notation
I know if you are familiar with this means
? is a function that is parameterize by ? right
and whatever specific value argue for ? will
define what that ? is okay and then this means
it is going to take some other argument okay,
so this is the input to the function okay.
Which is defined by these parameters ? okay
so this is how way when you put a semicolon
here that means it is forever transformed
okay arms are tight from taking all the notes
is all okay fine yeah, so since ?A; ? means
that is the policy defined by the current
settings of parameters ? times the Q * A right
because Q* A is a two expectation for taking
our may later and then some overall A I will
basically get the expected reward but if I
am having a deterministic policy that means
essentially only one arm I will take all the
other arms of probability 0 then the payoff
will be Q*of the term right okay, so now once
I have this kind of a performance measure
so what do I do is essentially I take ?.
.
They take ?, I find the gradient of the performance
okay so where the gradient is taken with respect
to ? right so I look at how the performance
changes with changing ? and I will try to
move ? in the direction of the increase in
the performance, okay. So this is called gradient
ascent the people might have heard about gradient
descent earlier so this is gradient descent,
so I am going up the gradient, right.
If the performance improves if I change ? in
some direction then I will change my ? in
that direction, okay that make sense we will
see this what we need more pictorial analogies
right, so let us say that a one parameter
? we also have one parameter ? right and ? (?) let
us say this nice it would be to do it right
let us say that I have my performance whatever
is an acceptable range of ? so my performance
goes like this right.
So I initially start off with some guess for
? and that will be my initial guess for ? right
then what I do, I measure this and then I
compute the gradient right so the gradient
is there so if I look at which direction I
should move my ?, essentially I should move
in this direction so I move a little bit and
set that as ?1 okay then I measure the radiant
again okay still I have to move in this direction
more so I keep doing that and I think I will
declare that I have reached the highest performance
there.
So this is essentially how I do it okay so
a couple of questions which you might ask
me here, why do I have to do this in this
kind of an incremental fashion why cannot
I just take the derivative of that and find
the highest point and settle down there, sorry
I do not have the function at all so I get
a good close form I do not have the function
at all what is it function that is Q*A( ?) right
I know ? but I do not know Q*.
The federal Q* my problem is solved right
I do not need to do any of these things that
function itself I do not know right so how
am I evaluating this function and trying to
find the gradient by sampling so I am pulling
a lot of farms right according to my current
policy ? right and then I am trying to evaluate
the policy ? and trying to find a gradient
at that point right, so because everything
is done through sampling.
So whatever gradient I compute at this point
will not be the correct gradient right this
is too simple when it has to either be that
direction or this direction this is too simple
right but think of a multi dimensional case
when there are many parameters the right direction
you will have to compute can get messed up
right so instead of going in all the parameters
in stuff identifying the right direction some
parameters you might get the right direction
some parameters you will get the wrong direction
and so on so forth right.
Therefore every time you make only small steps
because if we tried if we say oh I have computed
the direction of the gradient I will just
keep moving in the direction until my power
I will take a huge step in the direction until
my performance drops or something that would
not work because the direction itself might
be wrong so in this case I mean we have always
moved in the right direction every step.
That is possible that because you are estimating
the gradient you might actually can make the
wrong computations and move in the wrong direction
sometimes okay so what really you can hope
for from these kinds of methods which are
called stochastic gradient approaches okay
they are called stochastic gradient approaches
because you do not know the true gradient
and every time you make an estimate of what
he true gradient will be and then you are
using that for making moves.
I mean the most popular form of this will
be called SGD which is stochastic gradient
descent okay it is a very popular optimization
technique nowadays but in this case you are
using stochastic gradient descent but still
it is the same stochastic gradient idea and
so you have to be careful of how we use it
and the best that you can hope to get this
that in an expected sense over many updates
right.
I did I did know I showed you two updates
so if you make this update says this kind
of updates many times in an expected sense
you will move in the right direction of the
gradient right so that is the kind of guarantee
that typically expect for these kinds of methods
okay, so is it clear now is clearer now if
people are not hundred percent clear about
what I am talking a stop and ask and I can
elaborate at the risk of slowing down yeah.
Good point yeah so we will come to that so
you can talk about this is we do not know
the function itself right how are you going
to estimate the gradient right, so we will
come to that in a minute
so we know we have a functional form for this
now I am going to write down the gradient
for this expression right this is expression
we here I am going to write down the gradient
for this expression.
So this is assuming that Q * A because it
is a parameter of the problem right it is
nothing to do with the policy made as far
as your policy parameterization is concerned
Q star is a constant right because it is a
it is something to do with the problem so
I can I do not have to do this I just have
to differentiate this with respect to ? right,
so now I am going to do some hand waving.
So what did you do here a multiplied and divided
by ?, okay.
So for this to work what do I need ? is non
zero for all a so this is one condition that
you need for all of this any kind of ? that
you assume okay has to be nonzero for all
A I just assume some nonzero problem, now
if you think about this particular expression
right I will put a bracket around that right
so what does this remained you off, as it
look like an expectation computation I am
looking a the expected value of some function
right.
Were I am taking samples according to probability
? right this looks like an expected value
rate and summing over all possible outcomes
of A all possible values here right that is
the probability so I am essentially taking
the expectation taken according to ? of is
it fine right. So everybody on board with
it right so that I can write their expectation
oh okay sorry about the font, so the expectation
is taken with respect to ?, okay.
Is it clear so now we know how to make an
estimate of the expectations right how do
you do that we draw a sample and then take
an average right so we can do that so essentially
what I am going to do is pull an arm that
is a sample right when you say draw a sample
according to ? but essentially means I have
to pull an arm and what happens when I pull
an arm, I get a reward right but the reward
does not figure in here.
The expectation of the reward directly figures
in here a so I can actually write this as
a double expectation you know mean the expectation
is taken over not only ? but also over the
process that generates the reward Q* right
this also the process that generates the reward
so my sample here is going to consist of RT
right is it clear I mean this is a very subtle
thing a ripple or with me here on this is
it clear.
So Q* itself is already an expectation right
so instead of because I do not know this expectation
I will have to estimate this expectation as
well and that can be done by just taking the
RT’s so what I will do now is at every time
t I will sample or now I will pull the arm
figure out what the reward is right but is
that sufficient, no I have to do this right
I just cannot use the RT directly I have to
use this also right.
So I will take the gradient of ? so valuated
at A divided by the so this is my one sample
right this is because the expectation am taking
is of this quantity so the sample that I draw
is actually this right and I have to do this
over I do not know some number n ? 80 you
are right, defense oh no I am not using t
I am sorry if I promised you that I will use
n for discrete time and T for convenience
time.
So we are talking about discrete times here
it has to be n I do not know if i use T here
sorry about that but all of you a raise in
your notebook that T and write down N, for
this part of see things sorry about that right
so this is clear is that anything we see right,
so I need to have 1/ n that so this gives
me the radiant right so this is fine oh it
is still okay yet not because this is actually
a estimation okay.
So I cannot put equal to that it is only an
approximation rate so can we compute this,
we can right because we know ? we are the
ones who determine what ? should be right
because at the beginning I choose a parameterize
representation that I can choose whatever
suppose it is off max well I know how to take
the derivative of soft max at or if it is
a continuous actions I can just use a say
a Gaussian right I know how to take the derivative
of a Gaussian with respect to its parameters
right.
Or if it is a multinomial what do I do you
know how to take the derivative of a multinomial
as well right so the derivative is very simple
so I know what form of the function I choose
it so I can go ahead and take the derivative,
there are a couple of reasons for it
so estimating q store need not always be the
right thing to do okay because I have not
introduced all the complications and the hesitating
whether I should go there or not.
But the thing is so the Q*function sometimes
turns out to be incredibly complex okay as
a function of the state space okay not necessarily
here way as a function of the state space
q turns out to be incredibly complex where
as a direct representation of the policy turns
out to be a lot more simple right for example
there are many inventory control problems
where the policy essentially turns out to
be if the inventory is below a certain level
you buy inventories above a certain level
you do not buy okay.
But then the value function itself becomes
a very complicated function of how many of
the items are left of different types and
so on so forth so the function itself becomes
a lot harder to learn so there are instances
like this where this is easier to learn right
and there are a couple of other cases especially
when you are talking about very large problems
for example we will see that policy gradient
approaches generalize very easily to problems
with continuous actions.
So whether individual action super if you
are talking about value function methods right
where I typically store a value for each action
now I am going to have continuous actions
it is not clear how to handle it there are
ways of handling it but it turns out that
they are not that well behaved as policy gradient
approaches are and the action space is continuous
right so there are many reasons why you want
to consider the contractions I mean policy
critique metrics.
Primarily I would say the Prime one of the
primary motivations is to handle continues
actions, okay. So this is some kind of a batch
updates, what because the expectation is taken
with respect to the ?
now you could do more simplifications of that
if you want to write but what is your question
again, now but I need to take this expectation
with respect to the sample the probability
distribution ? right.
So and I cannot separate this I cannot write
this out I saw some really cannot simplify
this further because my Q* is here right so
this is the expectation of this whole quantity
so I really cannot split this apart and say
that okay I will just simplify this expectation
and take only the expected value of Q*A can
I, I cannot take E(AB) is not A (EFB) is it
in, A is only a constant rate not otherwise
I am not sure that we can simplify this further
right.
So what we are doing here is some kind of
a batch mode so if you think of how we are
doing this sampling so I am taking some ? fixing
it pulling the arms multiple times right fixing
? pulling arms capital n times and then taking
this average right and then or computing the
gradient and then using that to change the
parameters and this is one way of doing it
another way of doing it to stay that okay
I will have a ? I will pull an arm I will
compute the gradient. And I will change the
parameters wait so you can have a some kind
of an incremental version.
.
So where I am saying at every step I will
change my parameters by some fraction delta
T I will do this at every step right
sorry and so this is what I am doing so what
I am essentially will end up doing is ? will
be ? plus delta ?, ?n +1 will be ?n plus delta
?n right so this basically and I will do you
said every time you for every time I pull
an arm I will change this right I mean that
is essentially the gradient of the lawn it
turns out this simplifies your life a lot
this observation simplifies your life a lot
when you are trying to actually solve the
solve problems later right now you can immediately
think of soft max becoming very easy to differentiate
we have now taken log and there is also lots
of E’s there right.
So all the e power will thing will vanish
so it will become lot easier to differentiate
for you right so what I am going to do now
is to include another term here rather than
arbitrarily
called BN which we refer to as the reinforcement
baseline right and adding the BN should not
affect the whole process that is what the
BN should not really be a function of A yeah
? basically so it should not be a function
of the action I take right.
If it is a function of the action I take then
it becomes dependent on ? so as long as it
is not a function of the action I take I can
keep adding a I can add this thing it is called
the reinforcement baseline right so one way
of thinking about it is I am when I get a
reward right I do not know if the reward is
a good reward or a bad reward so giving a
baseline and saying that if you are above
this baseline it is a good reward if you are
below this baseline it is a bad reward.
It kind of allows you to calibrate the rewards
right one typical way in which this reinforcement
base line is used is to just take the average
of all the rewards I have obtained so far
later this is all the reverse regardless of
which are my play I keep accumulating the
rewards right now when I play a particular
arm if it is above this average then it is
a good down which below this average then
it is a bad arm right.
So valid after yeah I eventually it will eventually
it will be all fine right so initially you
might be making some mistakes because the
initial fury will B wrong right so you might
actually think a good arm is bad and a bad
arm is good I mean depending but eventually
it will all work out does not matter so if
you think about if the reward is good right
then I will go in the direction of the gradient
right but if the reward is bad and I will
go in the opposite direction of the gradient
right.
So in some sense that is a little waving hear
that but then it is fine it turns out that
adding the reinforcement baseline makes the
convergence behavior of this algorithm a little
more stable but it is not necessary you can
if you are going to implement this you can
do it without the reinforcement baseline also
right so this is called the
and this term is sometimes called the call
the characteristic eligibility.
So what is the characteristic eligibility
it essentially tells you, if you
do that then you get into a critic I will
talk about that later and talk about that
later yeah sure yeah you could do that right
and that is essentially the one of the motivations
for getting attacked or critical rhythms,
so that SN requires you to maintain Q star
estimates as well as the ? estimates as well
as a ? representation.
So the ? would be that critic and the Q star
would be the actor other way around the ? would
be the actor the Q star will be the critic
so that is another class of algorithms right
which address some of the drawbacks of policy
gradient approaches and so I will talk about
it but somewhere halfway down the course not
now so after this I am going to go back and
start talking about the full RL problem and
at some point I will come back and do a TRO
critic yeah.
So his question was why do I use RN right
why cannot I plug-in q there right you could
and yeah and typically when you do that it
performs better the algorithm it is actually
a it reduces variants significantly at the
cost of adding significant bias and there
are other issues you know you well you know
or other issue is going to actor critic but
I will talk about it later right and we are
going back.
So why is that called the characteristic eligibility
so if you think about it so it essentially
chooses which of the ? are most responsible
for a change at that point right so that is
the term that determines that is the term
that is the ? dependent term in your updates
right and it tells you which ? is more responsible
for change that is happening here there are
three or four different that I have right.
So whichever has the highest gradient whichever
direction you have the highest gradient that
is a direction where the largest change is
going to happen right, so it is essentially
this telling you which ? is more eligible
to receive the update that is why it is called
the characteristic eligibility I did that
make sense to people I think i have lost more
people today than in the previous classes
no great.
So this whole thing right this way of doing
this incremental version of doing this update
is actually called the called the reinforce
algorithm the first proposed by this guy called
Williams in 88, Williams suppose reinforce
in think in 1988 and in fact he proposed this
in the context of neural networks right so
he when he came up with this algorithm neural
networks were still ruling right.
So he proposed this in the context of neural
networks he said that your ? is our weights
of a neural network right and then he came
up with this update and then the biggest contribution
he did was he said that a this looks like
a really crazy update and I mean how is this
going to work and initially people are very
skeptical he actually showed that in an expected
sense that even though I am doing this update
after just pulling one arm in an expected
since the gradient will be in the right direction
right.
If I repeat this experiment multiple times
and I watch how the weights evolve right they
will actually move in the same direction as
it would have happened if I had computed the
correct gradient and then taken steps in that
direction so essentially he established that
for this reinforce update and it since then
it has kind of been the one sole hope of convergence
for all kinds of complex function approximations
and RL okay.
So it works really well but it is extreme
extremely, reinforce is extremely slow because
the variance is very high so when I want to
move on from this I will talk about the other
problems of reinforce here is a horrible part
about the paper so reinforce is actually an
acronym there is an expansion each letter
stands actually for a word he came up with
a name for the algorithm which actually shortened
to reinforce.
And then that started the trend for convoluted
names in him since the RL community okay anyone
knows what the expansion of real food you
know what the expansion of reinforces forgot
okay, I cannot for the life of me I refuse
to memorize what reinforce transform, great
so let us do some special cases of reinforce
right I want to consider a binary bandit.
.
Or let us say I take it banded with two actions
okay but they can have arbitrary rewards here
is the parameterization I choose this is essentially
the Bernoulli thing rights I have two actions
so some probability ? I will select action
1,1-? I will select action 0 so what do I
need to do now to get that update rule we
have to find ? ln ?/ ?? so what this will
be, it will be1 VI is one it will be maybe
minus 1 here.
If correct no yeah look at Log ? it is not
??/ ?? yeah so it will be 1/ ? via is one
and it will be -1/1-F if it case zero right,
can read it like that this of two day is1
so 1 minus ? or minus ETA will get cancelled
out will get 1 by ? this up today is zero
? and ? will get cancelled out we will get
minus 1 by1 minus ? okay the compact way of
writing it and now I am going to say that
I will choose my a to be some row times ? x
1-?.
So it turns out that as long as your a is
not dependent on the actual reward that you
get okay it can be dependent on the ? this
is what William should as long is not dependent
on the actual reward you are all fine okay
you will converge so that is essentially this
is result so I can make it dependent on by
? it should not be dependent on the actual
action you sample okay and the actual reward
that you receive so as long as that is there
it is fine all right.
And I am going to choose my be to be 0 why
am I making this specific choices so now I
let me plug everything back in so what does
my Delta ? look like, so a n which is ? into
? n 1 minus ?n 2 RN minus B this is 0 so it
is RN into dole on this which will be A- ? /? x
1-? right so what we end up getting row okay
so what is the what is the interpretation
for this, let us say I take action one can
and I get a reward of 1.
So what do I get ? into 1 minus ? that is
how much I change my value by so it is essentially
this right ? 1-? right suppose I took action
but what about I took action one right and
my reward was one that what will I do for
0 oh there is no way there is only one parameter
it is automatically my other parameter will
get our district because it is 1-? suppose
I took action one and got a reward of 0 what
happens no change.
Suppose I took action of 0 and got A reward
of 1 what happens, minus ? into RL right so
that is essentially what I have here right
so this is minus ? into RL right so ? is my
piet-80 if you remember right and then this
is so that is essentially what I have, so
this is this is what LR I right so essentially
LR I is a is a gradient following algorithm
actually it is a reinforce algorithm right
so you can try to look at different choices
for the as and the different choices for ? right
and try to come up with this kind of update
rule right.
We will do the soft max action selection as
I described in the previous class right so
do that right where I replace all my Q’s
with some arbitrary ? suppose I have K actions
or K arms then I will have ?1 to ? K these
are my parameters and the probability of selecting
are my will be e ? I/ß divided by summation
over j e ? I/ß right so this is my soft max
expression so derive my reinforce update rules
assuming the fixed pressure, right that is
one I am going to give you another homework.
The same thing I said one of the nice things
about doing reinforce.
.
Is it allows us to handle continues actions
right allows us to handle continuous actual
actions need not be discreet so far way be
looking at the cases or actions are discreet
so I am going to use that is my probability
distribution that is my policy okay give me
the reinforce update rules so how many rules
will I have for reinforce update rules there
one for the µ one for the s right.
Get me the reinforce update rules and yeah
so try to simplify as much as possible because
when you do the log µ I mean the log ? derivatives
will get all kinds of we had constants coming
there so you can choose your a appropriately
so that some of these constants get cancelled
out so that I can have again just like we
did here right I chose my road to be ? into
1minus ? likewise you can choose your constants
in this case also write the ? has to be something
different so that you end up with a good nice-looking
form okay great.